and I'm going to talk about what an alpha male is, because I think we can all learn a lot from our close relatives where we have alpha males. And as an example, I want to give you Amos, a male that I knew who was a young male and he was alpha male, he was very popular, but he got sick and he lost his position because, you know, chimpanzee males they can spot from a mile away if you are weak and they went for him, and he lost his position, and then he got sicker and sicker until at some point we had to isolate him. The group lived on a grassy island, and we had to isolate him in a cage, but we cracked open the cage so that the rest of the chimps still had access to him. And what happened was most touching. Other chimps would bring food to him, they would bring wood wool to him, which is this thing that they use to sleep in and build nests out of, and females would put the wood wool behind his back. He was leaning heavily against the wall, and the way we do with pillows to patients in a hospital, they were putting that stuff behind his back. And I thought, this is the way to go for an alpha male. He was loved and respected, and everyone was taking care of him, and this is not always how it goes, because some males don't end so well when they lose their position. So Amos was an example of a male who was liked as a leader, and I think the term alpha male, if you look it up on the internet, you will find all these business books that tell you how to be an alpha male, and what they mean is how to beat up others and beat them over the head and let them know that you are boss and don't mess with me and so on. And basically an alpha male for them is a bully. And I really don't like that kind of description, because I am actually partly responsible for the term "alpha male" because I wrote this book "Chimpanzee Politics," which was recommended by Newt Gingrich to freshmen congressmen. I don't know what good it did, but he recommended that book to them, and after that the term "alpha male" became very popular. But I think it is used in a mischaracterization. It's used in a very superficial way that doesn't relate to what a real alpha male is. And so I'm here to explain what that is. The term itself goes back actually much further. It goes back to the '40s and '50s, research on wolves, and basically the definition is very simple. The highest ranking male is the alpha male. The highest ranking female is the alpha female. Every primate group has one alpha male, one alpha female, not more than that, there's only one.
y voy a hablarles de lo que es un macho alfa, porque creo que podemos aprender mucho de nuestros parientes cercanos, entre los que hay machos alfa. Como ejemplo, quiero presentarles a Amos, un macho que conocí, un macho alfa joven, muy popular, pero se enfermó y perdió su lugar, porque los chimpancés machos son capaces de detectar a la distancia si alguien está débil, por eso fueron por él, y perdió su posición. y fue enfermándose más y más hasta que en un momento tuvimos que aislarlo. El grupo vivía en una isla cubierta de pastizales, y tuvimos que aislarlo en una jaula, pero dejamos la jaula abierta para que los otros chimpancés siguieran teniendo acceso a él. Y lo que ocurrió entonces fue muy conmovedor. Los otros chimpancés le traían comida, le llevaban virutas de madera, que suelen usar para acostarse y hacer sus nidos, y las hembras le ponían las virutas detrás de la espalda. Amos estaba recostado contra la pared, y a modo de almohada, como si estuviera en un hospital, le ponían ese material detrás de la espalda. Y pensé: "Así es como se debe tratar a un macho alfa". Era querido y respetado, y todos lo cuidaban, pero no siempre es así, porque algunos no terminan tan bien cuando pierden su lugar. Amos era ejemplo de un macho que gustaba como líder, y si buscamos el término "macho alfa" en Internet, hallaremos libros de negocios que enseñan a ser un macho alfa, es decir a cómo ser superiores a los demás, cómo pasarles por encima y demostrarles quién es el jefe y que no deben meterse con uno. En este contexto, el macho alfa es básicamente un bravucón. A decir verdad, es una descripción que no comparto porque, en parte, soy responsable del término "macho alfa" por ser autor del libro "La política de los chimpancés", que recomendó Newt Gingrich a los miembros del Congreso. Desconozco cuán útil les pudo ser, lo cierto es que se los recomendó. y, desde entonces, el término "macho alfa" se popularizó mucho. Pero considero que se lo interpreta de manera equivocada. Se usa de una manera muy superficial que no se relaciona con lo que es, en verdad, un macho alfa. Por eso vine, para explicar lo que significa. El término en sí mismo se remonta a mucho antes. Se remonta a investigaciones con lobos en los años 40 y 50, y la definición es, en esencia, muy sencilla. El macho de mayor rango es el macho alfa. La hembra de mayor rango es la hembra alfa. Cada grupo de primates tiene un macho alfa, una hembra alfa, no hay otro, es solo uno.
And I will explain how that goes. So first, the body language. What you see here is two male chimpanzees who are the same size, but one is walking upright, has his hair up,
Les explicaré cómo funciona. Veamos, en primer lugar, el lenguaje corporal. Vemos aquí dos machos del mismo tamaño, pero uno camina erguido, con el pelaje erizado,
has a big rock in his hand, and he's the alpha male. The other male is pant-grunting to him, is being submissive to him and bowing for him, and that is the sort of ritual they need to go through many times a day in order to have a stable relationship. I'll show you a video from the field. What you will see here is a female pant-grunting to an alpha male and you will see how that goes. The male is approaching, she grunts at him. (Chimpanzee grunts) He has all his hair up and he displays. I'm actually standing far too close. A chimpanzee is far stronger than I am, and I just was not very prudent, this particular video. So what you saw him do is he was lifting himself up and standing on two legs, and putting his arms out. That's called the bipedal swagger. It's a very common posture in high-ranking males, and it's very recognizable because humans do this kind of stuff. (Laughter) Humans do this all the time. And what I really like about this particular picture is the two old guys to the side. This is very chimpanzee. In chimpanzees, we have usually old males who are over the hill, who cannot be alpha male themselves anymore, but they start playing games and forming coalitions, and behind the backs of others. And they become extremely influential, and you may actually have old males who are more influential than the alpha male himself.
tiene una gran piedra en la mano y es el macho alfa. El otro macho le gruñe, se somete a él y se inclina y ese es el tipo de ritual que hacen varias veces al día para poder mantener una relación estable. Les mostraré un vídeo filmado en el lugar. Vemos una hembra que le gruñe a un macho alfa y observen qué sucede. El macho se acerca, ella le gruñe. (El chimpancé gruñe) El macho tiene el pelaje erizado y presume ante la hembra. Yo estoy allí, muy cerca de ellos. Un chimpancé es mucho más fuerte que yo, y no fui muy prudente con este vídeo en particular. Lo que acaban de ver es al macho erguido sobre sus dos patas, abriendo los brazos. Eso se llama pavoneo bípedo. Es una postura muy común entre machos de alto rango, y es reconocible porque los humanos también lo hacen. (Risas) Lo hacen todo el tiempo. Lo que más me gusta de esta foto son los dos hombres a los costados. Esto es típico de los chimpancés. En los chimpancés, hay machos entrados en años que ya no pueden ser machos alfa, pero empiezan a hacer ardides y a formar alianzas a espaldas del resto, y se vuelven extremadamente influyentes. Incluso puede haber machos ancianos que tienen más influencia que el propio macho alfa.
Just as an example, the three males that I used to work with most at the Dutch zoo long ago, where I worked, and the middle male here is a 17-year-old alpha male. The male whom he is grooming on the side is twice as old, and this old male has made him the leader. So you can imagine that that old male has an enormous amount of power, because he has made the alpha male alpha male. The male on the right is individually the strongest male. In captivity, you can test it out, and you can know that this male has no trouble with either one. He has only trouble with the combination of the two. And so the coalition formation that goes on in chimpanzee society makes it much more complex than you think. It means, for example, that the smallest male in a group can be the alpha male. You don't need to be the biggest and strongest male. The smallest male, if he has the right friends and keeps them happy, or he has female support, he can be the alpha male. So the coalition system makes everything complex, and I'm always waiting here in the US for the primaries, the end of the primaries, because that's a moment where you need to demonstrate unity. Now let me first show you how the unity is shown in chimpanzees. What you see here is two males on the left who are standing together. You also see the big canine teeth that they have. And they're standing together and they demonstrate to the rest of the group, "We are together. We are a unit." The males on the right are walking together in synchrony. That's another way of demonstrating that you are together. And so demonstrating unity is extremely important in a coalition system, and as I said, in the primaries always I'm waiting for that moment because then you have two members of the same party who have been fighting with each other, and they need to come together at some moment. And it leads to very awkward situations.
Por ejemplo, de estos tres machos, que son con los que más trabajé hace tiempo en el zoológico holandés, en el que trabajé el del medio es el macho alfa, de 17 años de edad. El macho al que está acicalando lo dobla en edad, y es él quien lo eligió como líder. Está claro que ese macho anciano tiene un poder enorme, porque fue quien ungió al macho alfa como tal. El macho de la derecha es el más fuerte a nivel individual. Esto se hace evidente cuando están en cautiverio, porque no tiene conflicto con ninguno de los otros dos. El conflicto surge cuando aquellos dos están juntos. Las alianzas que se forman en esa sociedad hacen que sea más compleja de lo que uno cree. Esto significa, por ejemplo, que el macho más pequeño del grupo puede ser el macho alfa. No hace falta que sea el más grande ni el más fuerte. Si el más chico mantiene contentos a los amigos adecuados o si tiene el apoyo de las hembras, puede ser el macho alfa. Vemos que el sistema de coaliciones complica las cosas. Yo siempre espero las primarias aquí en EE. UU., el final de las primarias, porque es el momento en que se debe demostrar unidad. Primero, vean cómo ellos muestran unidad. Lo que ven aquí a la izquierda son dos machos que están juntos. También vean los grandes dientes caninos que tienen. Al mostrarse juntos, comunican al resto del grupo "Estamos juntos. Somos una unidad". Los machos de la derecha caminan juntos en sincronía. Esa es otra manera de demostrar que son aliados. Demostrar unidad es sumamente importante en un sistema de coaliciones y, como dije antes, siempre espero ese momento en las primarias porque luego aparecen dos miembros del mismo partido que antes se habían enfrentado y en un momento dado tienen que mostrarse juntos. Y así se producen situaciones sumamente incómodas.
People who don't like each other need to embrace each other and stand together, and that's absolutely essential for the unity of the party, and if you don't do that, the party may fall apart. And so if it doesn't go well, like in this particular case -- (Laughter) then the party is in deep doo-doo because they have not demonstrated unity. So that's a very important part of the coalition system, and that's something that we share between humans and chimpanzees. Now, how do you become an alpha male? First of all, you need to be impressive and intimidating and demonstrate your vigor on occasion and show that you are very strong, and there's all sorts of ways of doing that.
Personas que no se agradan se ven obligadas a abrazarse y a mostrarse juntas, lo cual es fundamental para la unidad del partido, y si no lo hacen, el partido puede colapsar. Y si no funciona, como en este caso particular, (Risas) el partido tendrá problemas por no demostrar unidad. En fin, la unidad es fundamental en el sistema de coaliciones, y es algo que compartimos con los chimpancés. Ahora veamos cómo se llega a ser macho alfa. En primer lugar, es importante impresionar, infundir temor, demostrar poder cuando sea necesario y hacer manifestación de fuerza. Hay muchas formas de hacerlo.
But other things that you need to do is you need to be generous. So, for example, males who go on a campaign to dethrone the leader, which may take two or three months where they're testing all the coalitions in the group, they also become extremely generous. They share food very easily with everyone. Or they start to tickle the babies of the females. They're normally, male chimpanzees, not particularly interested in infants, but when they are campaigning like that, they get very interested in infants and they tickle them, and they try to curry favor with the females. (Laughter) So in humans, of course, I am always intrigued by these men who are candidates
Pero el macho alfa también debe ser generoso. Por ejemplo, los machos que intentan derrocar al líder, una campaña que puede llevar dos o tres meses, para controlar las coaliciones que se dan en el grupo, también demuestran una gran generosidad. Comparten la comida abiertamente con los demás. O les hacen cosquillas a los bebés de las hembras. Los chimpancés machos no son particularmente afectos a las crías, pero cuando están en campaña se acercan y las divierten de esta manera, y así se ganan la simpatía de las hembras. (Risas) Volviendo a los humanos, siempre me intrigaron los candidatos varones
and hold babies up like this. This is not particularly something that babies like -- (Laughter) but since it is a signal to the rest of the world, they need to hold them in the air. And I was really intrigued by, when we had a female candidate in the last election, the way she held babies was more like this, which is what babies really like. But she of course didn't need to send the message that she could hold a baby without dropping it, which was what the man was doing. So this is a very common tactic, and male chimpanzees, they spend a lot of time currying favor with all sorts of parties when they are campaigning. Now, what are the privileges and the costs of being an alpha male? The biggest privilege is females. Food is really irrelevant. Male chimpanzees can go a week without food if there's a female in estrus and they're sexually interested in her.
que alzan a los bebés así. No es algo que agrade particularmente a los bebés, (Risas) pero como es una señal que será vista en todo el mundo, tienen que sostener alzado al niño. Y algo que me llamó la atención, cuando participó una mujer en las últimas elecciones, fue que ella tomaba a los bebés en esta posición, que es la que agrada a los bebés. Pero, claro, no necesitaba transmitir el mensaje de que podía sostenerlo sin que se le cayera, a diferencia del hombre que sí lo necesitaba. Es una táctica muy común, y los chimpancés machos intentan a menudo congraciarse con distintos partidos cuando están en campaña. Ahora, ¿cuáles son el precio y los privilegios de ser un macho alfa? El mayor privilegio lo constituyen las hembras. La comida no tiene importancia. Los machos pueden pasarse una semana sin comer cuando una hembra está en celo y los machos la pretenden.
Food is secondary to sex. And so the male chimpanzees -- and we evolutionary biologists, of course, we have an explanation for this, is that sex leads to reproduction, and reproductive success is the measure of evolution. That's how everything evolves. And so if males can enhance their reproductive success by being high ranking, you get automatically the ambition to be high ranking in the males. So that's the privilege. The costs, one cost is of course that you need to keep your partners happy. So if you come to power with the support of an old male, you need to let that old male mate with females. If you don't do that, that old male is going to get mad at you, and you're going to lose him as a partner.
La comida es secundaria al sexo. Los machos actúan de este modo, según nuestra teoría como biólogos evolucionistas, porque el sexo conduce a la reproducción y el éxito reproductivo es la medida de la evolución. Así es como evoluciona todo. Y por eso, si los machos mejoran su rol reproductivo ascendiendo de rango, automáticamente querrán subir de posición entre los machos. Ese es el privilegio. Con respecto al precio que deben pagar, uno es que deben mantener a los socios contentos. Así, si alguno llega al poder con el apoyo de un anciano, pues ese macho anciano podrá aparearse con las hembras. Si no es así, entonces ese macho se enfadará, retirará su apoyo y ya dejarán de ser socios.
So there's a transaction going on. If you become alpha male this way, you need to keep your partners happy. And so that's one of the costs. The second cost is that everyone wants your position. Alpha male position is a very important position, and everyone wants to take it from you, and so you constantly have to watch your back. You have to be extremely vigilant.
Así que hay una transacción. Si el macho llega al rango alfa así, deberá contentar a sus socios. Ese es un precio que debe pagar. El segundo es que todos quieren esa posición. El rango de macho alfa es muy importante, y todos quieren arrebatarlo, por eso debe siempre cuidar sus espaldas, debe estar sumamente alerta.
For example, you have to disrupt the coalitions of others and that's what male chimpanzees do quite a bit.
Por ejemplo, debe disolver las alianzas ajenas, algo que hacen a menudo.
Divide and rule strategies, they have. And so that's a very stressful situation, and we actually have data on this. The data comes from the field, from baboons not chimpanzees in this case, where they did fecal samples on the baboons and they analyzed them for glucocorticoids. And what you see here is a graph where you see that the lower ranking the male baboon is, the higher is his cortisol level in the feces,
Aplican la estrategia de "divide y reinarás". Esta situación genera gran estrés, que pudimos comprobar muy bien a través de datos obtenidos en el lugar, con babuinos, no con chimpancés esta vez, donde se recogieron muestras fecales de los babuinos y se analizaron los glucocorticoides. Vemos aquí un gráfico donde el babuino macho de menor jerarquía registra los niveles más altos de cortisol en sus heces.
but the alpha male, as you see, has just as high a level as the lowest-ranking males, and so you may think that being alpha male is nice and dandy and is wonderful, but it's actually a very stressful position, and we can demonstrate that physiologically. Now, what are the obligations? And here, for me, it gets really interesting, and it deviates very much from your typical image of the alpha male. The alpha male has two sorts of obligations. One is to keep the peace in the group. We call that the control role, to control fights in the group,
Pero, como pueden ver, el macho alfa llega al mismo nivel que el macho de menor rango, y de esto se podría inferir que ser macho alfa es genial, pero en realidad es una posición de gran estrés, lo cual queda demostrado en el plano fisiológico. Ahora, ¿cuáles son las obligaciones? Y este aspecto me parece sumamente interesante, que se aparta de la típica imagen que tenemos del macho alfa. El macho alfa tiene dos obligaciones. Una es mantener la paz dentro del grupo. Le llamamos "rol de control", o controlar las luchas del grupo.
and the second is to be the most empathic, the consoler in chief, basically, of the nation, so to speak. So first of all, keeping the peace. This is a male who stops a fight between two females. Two females on the left and the right have been screaming and yelling at each other over food, because food is very important for the females, and so he stops the fight between them and stands between them like this. And it's very interesting to me that alpha males, when they do this, they become impartial. They don't support their mom or their best buddy. No, no, they stop fights, and they come up for the underdog in general. And this makes them extremely popular in the group, because they provide security for the lowest-ranking members of the group. And so they become impartial, which is an unusual condition for a chimpanzee to be in, because they're usually very fond of their friends and so on, and these alpha males who are good at this, they can be very effective at keeping the peace in the group. And the second thing they do is they show empathy for others. Now, I do an enormous amount of research on empathy, and I don't have time to go into it, but empathy is nowadays a topic that we study in rodents and dogs and elephants and primates, all sorts of animals. And what you see here is two bonobos. The one in front has been beaten up in a fight. The one in the back puts her arms around her and consoles her. This is also actually how we measure empathy in young children, by looking at how they respond to distressed individuals. And high-ranking males, they do a lot of this. High-ranking males provide an enormous amount of comfort in the group, and they go to places where there are earthquakes or hurricanes and they provide comfort. The pope does this. The presidents do this. All the leaders in the world have to do this job. The queen does it and so on. They all have to do this job, so providing consolation, and that's a very important task. And males who are good at these two, keeping the peace and providing comfort, they become extremely popular leaders, and there's actually some self-interest involved in it. They don't do it just for the group, because it also stabilizes their position. The more popular a male becomes as alpha male and the more the rest of them respects them and looks up to them, the better their position is defended in case it's going to be challenged by somebody else, because then, of course, the whole group is going to support that male because they want to keep a leader who is good for them. So the group is usually very supportive of males who are good leaders, and it's not supportive at all of bullies.
La segunda es manifestar la mayor empatía posible, encargarse de consolar a los demás, por decirlo así. Así que, lo primero es mantener la paz. Vemos aquí un macho que detiene la lucha entre dos hembras. Las dos hembras a la izquierda y la derecha se han estado agrediendo y gritando por comida, porque la comida es muy importante para ellas, entonces el macho se interpone y para la pelea de esta manera. Me parece sumamente interesante que los machos alfa sean imparciales aquí. No se inclinan por su madre ni por su mejor amigo. No, no, detienen la pelea y, en general, se ponen del lado del más débil. Esto los hace extremadamente populares dentro del grupo, porque les da seguridad a los miembros de menor rango. Adoptan una postura imparcial, algo poco común en los chimpancés, porque en general son muy afectos a sus compañeros, y estos machos alfa que saben hacerlo pueden mantener la paz en el grupo de manera efectiva. La segunda obligación es mostrar empatía por el resto. Personalmente, me dedico a investigar sobre la empatía, y no puedo ahora explayarme, pero la empatía es, hoy día, tema de estudio en roedores, perros, elefantes y primates, y muchos otros animales. Vemos aquí dos bonobos hembras. La que está adelante ha sido derrotada en una pelea. La hembra de atrás la abraza a modo de consuelo. En realidad, es así como medimos la empatía en los niños, viendo cómo reaccionan ante el sufrimiento ajeno. Los machos de alto rango actúan así muy seguido. Consuelan profundamente a los miembros del grupo y van a sitios que han sido afectados por terremotos o huracanes y allí brindan consuelo. Lo hace el papa, lo hace el presidente. Todos los líderes del mundo deben hacerlo. La reina también lo hace. Todos tienen que hacerlo, brindar consuelo, que es una tarea fundamental. Los machos que cumplen bien estas dos funciones, mantener la paz y dar consuelo, se vuelven líderes enormemente populares, y, en verdad, estas actitudes encierran cierto interés personal. No lo hacen solo por el grupo, sino porque además estabiliza su posición. Cuanto más popular se hace un macho alfa, y cuanto más admirado y respetado sea por los demás, tanto más defendido será su lugar en caso de que algún otro macho pretenda su puesto, porque, obviamente, tendrá el apoyo de todo el grupo, que querrá conservar un líder que es bueno para ellos. El grupo suele ser muy solidario con los buenos líderes, no así con los machos bravucones.
And when bullies lose their position, they may end up in a very bad situation there. This is data actually on the consolation behavior. This is data on consolation in chimpanzees, and you see for the medium- and low-ranking individuals, the females do more of it than the males. This is basically the whole community. And this is true for all the mammal studies on empathy is that females have more of it than males. But look at the alpha male. The alpha male does far more than anybody else. And so that's the data on alpha males being the consoler in chief, basically. The last thing I want to say is something about alpha females. This is a picture of Mama, the alpha female in the Arnhem zoo where I used to work, who is now all over the internet, I think a hundred million clicks at the moment, for a video of her dying at the age of 59, which happened last year. And Mama was an absolute centrum of the group. So she was not physically capable of dominating the males. She ranked below the males, but she was the center of the community, and if there was big trouble in the community, everyone would end up in the arms of Mama. And so she was a very important figure. And so I don't want to minimize the position of alpha females
Cuando los bravucones pierden su posición, pueden terminar muy mal. Vemos aquí datos relativos al comportamiento solidario. Son datos sobre la actitud de consuelo de los chimpancés, y se observa que, entre los de rango medio y alto, las hembras son más solidarias que los machos. Esto aplica a toda la comunidad. Esto se repite en todos los estudios con mamíferos, donde las hembras muestran más empatía que los machos. Pero si miramos al macho alfa, su conducta es más marcada que la de los demás. Según los datos, los machos alfa muestran mayor empatía. Quisiera terminar refiriéndome a las hembras alfa. Aquí está Mama, la hembra alfa del zoológico de Arnhem, que era donde trabajaba, y está ahora por toda Internet. Llegó a las cien millones de visualizaciones por un vídeo del momento de su muerte a los 59 años, ocurrida el año pasado. Mama era el centro absoluto del grupo. No tenía la capacidad física de dominar a los machos. Tenía menor rango que ellos, pero era el centro de todo, y siempre que había un conflicto todos terminaban en brazos de Mama. Era sin duda una figura central. Por eso, no se debe minimizar la posición de las hembras alfa
in the chimpanzee group. And then we have a species that is equally close to us as the chimpanzee, the bonobo. We often forget about the bonobo, but the bonobos have a matriarchal society
en el grupo de los chimpancés. Y luego tenemos una especie igual de cercana a nosotros que los chimpancés: los bonobos. Solemos olvidarlos, pero ellos tienen una sociedad matriarcal
and the alpha individual is a female, generally. Generally, it's a female who is at the top of the community, and we know much less about how this is done and how they get to that position, and what they do with it, because we know much less about bonobos in general. But I do want to emphasize that the alpha in a group doesn't need to be a male, and that actually in one of our close relatives, it is a female. So the message I want to leave you with is that if you are looking at men in our society who are the boss of, let's say, a family or a business or Washington or whatever, you call them alpha male, you should not insult chimpanzees by using the wrong label. (Laughter) You should not call a bully an alpha male. Someone who is big and strong and intimidates and insults everyone is not necessarily an alpha male. An alpha male has all sorts of qualities, and I have seen bully alpha males in chimpanzees, they do occur, but most of the ones that we have have leadership capacities and are integrated in their community, and, like Amos at the end, they are loved and respected, and so it's a very different situation than you may think. And I thank you. (Applause)
y la figura alfa suele ser una hembra. Ocupa el rango más alto de la comunidad, y se tiene muy poca información sobre cómo acceden a ese lugar y qué funciones cumplen, porque, en general, la información que tenemos es limitada. Pero sí quiero remarcar que la figura alfa del grupo no es necesariamente un macho, y que, en el caso de estos parientes, es una hembra. El mensaje que quiero dejarles es que si un hombre de nuestra sociedad es el jefe, por ejemplo, de una familia, una empresa, Washington, o lo que fuere, y es llamado el "macho alfa", no deberíamos ofender a los chimpancés etiquetando equivocadamente. (Risas) Un bravucón no debería ser tildado de macho alfa. Alguien grande y fuerte que intimida e insulta a los demás no es necesariamente un macho alfa. Un macho alfa tiene todo tipo de cualidades, y he visto machos alfa bravucones entre los chimpancés, los hay, pero en su mayoría tienen cualidades de liderazgo y están integrados a la comunidad, y al igual que Amos al final, son queridos y respetados, que es una situación muy distinta de la que solemos imaginar. Gracias. (Aplausos)